<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><salutation>r Wardell Pameroy
Institute for sex research 
Indiana University
Bloomington Ind
Dear Sir,</salutation>
   <page num="1"> I was given your name by an acquaintance of mine Mrs. <redacted type="acquaintance">[redacted]</redacted>, as she thought 
    you would have as much knowledge about a problem that faces our family as anyone in the country. 
    Our twenty eight year old son had a complete nervous break down while in the service and has been in 
    the metropolitan state hospital near los angeles past three years. 
I have gone to the family conference nearly every month and the doctors just smile charmingly and tell me nothing. 
After deciding he must be hopeless, his present doctor thinks he is well enough to come home, 
although he says he is a chronic case and could become ill</page>

PAGE 2
again.
<page num="2">The doctors have asked me several times before if we would let  <redacted type="son">[redacted]</redacted> come home 
    to live and I have said no because my husband has been quite ill with a stomach ulcer for several years 
    and at times has been unbearably irritable. In November he finally underwent an operation and it has been 
    very successful. He can now eat anything is free from pain, and his nerves are improving so I finally said [redacted] could come home.
First I said I thought a home care placement would be better and the social workers said [redacted] 
couldn’t enter a foster home due to his bad sex habits. I asked her what they were, 
and to my utter amazement and horror she said he had homosexual tendencies but was not overt and was much better.
I suppose I am unbelievably stupid but I had never even thought of </page>

PAGE 3
<page num="3">Such a possibility. My husband and I went to the hospital last thrusday to try to find out more and again the doctor would tell us nothing but he did say “he hadn’t said [redacted] had homosexual tendencies and had seen no signs of such behavior while he had beehn in charge of the ward.
A chaplain who also attended the metting and (who evidentily felt concerned over our deep destress), followed us out when the meeting ended. He said he had talked to [redacted] often, and had see his chart and that homosexuality was not mentioned on the chart.
He did say however that [redacted] was asexual. That he had not developed sexuality and was still about a fourteen year old boy. 
While that was hard enough to take the chaplain was as kind(?) he seemed to lift a great load off my shoulders. </page>
PAGE 4
<page num="4">Now I want to know can anything be done develop [redacted] sexuality or will he always remain as he is?
Mr. James Peterson of the U.S.C councils at our church and I wonder if it would be necessary for [redacted] to have psychiatric conference. at present he seems quite cheerful but the chaplin [redacted] feels his is a failure as a man, with girls, and with his work. These feeling can’t continue or he might try suicide again.
What more can we do for him? He will live with us. I have found a self aid work home there which employs only handicapped men. 
The men can work as their own speed. There doing simple production line work. And they are kindly treated. 
I hope he will work there at least</page>

PAGE 5
<page num="5">For a while and we have him __ with the Peterson is there anything more that can be done, and is there any hope that he will ever be mature ___ sexually to marry? Physically he is attractive looking and very normal and certainly not feminine in any way.
    Who is actually correct. The social worker or the chaplain? I hope the latter</page>

Yours, truly,
    <redacted type="mother">[redacted]</redacted>
P.S
Is there anyone out here that I could take my son to for treatment?
</root>
