<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>
               <title xmlns="">Asexual and Autoerotic Women: Two Invisible Groups</title>/
                        </title>
            <author>
               <addName/>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <body xmlns="">
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="main">
               <head>ASEXUAL AND AUTOEROTIC WOMEN: TWO INVISIBLE GROUPS</head>
               <p>Myra T. Johnson</p>
               <figure xmlns="">
                  <blockquote>
                     <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
            No more fiendish punishment could be devised, were such a thing
            physically possible, than that one should be turned loose in a
            society and remain absolutely unnoticed by all the members thereof.
          </p>
                  </blockquote>
                  <figcaption>William James, <cite>Psychology</cite>
                  </figcaption>
               </figure>
               <p>
        The term <em xmlns="">asexual</em> is rarely used in scientific literature on
        human sexuality. When the word is recorded, its meaning is usually left
        vague, with its definitions ranging from "unexpressed" sexuality to
        "absence of sexual desire" due to "loss of the sex glands" or to
        psychiatric disorder (Johnson and Belzer, 1973: p.90; Hinsie and
        Campbell, 1970: p. 66). In current popular usage it often carries a
        pejorative connotation, as here:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          The least interesting character, of course, is Joan, a kind of
          <em xmlns="">asexual</em> coathanger on which to hang the banner of Marxist
          conversation. Joan's personality is not nearly so important as her
          manipulated goodness. (<cite xmlns="">Boston After Dark</cite>, Feb. 25, 1975:
          p. 6) (Italic added)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        This connotation of "manipulated goodness" is also evoked by such
        synonyms as <em xmlns="">celibate</em>, <em xmlns="">chaste</em>, and <em xmlns="">virgin</em>—all
        of which are identified, historically, with religious principles,
        <cite xmlns="">Webster's Seventh New Collegiate Dictionary</cite> (1963), for
        example, includes "abstention by vow from marriage" in its definitions
        of <em xmlns="">celibate</em>, describes a <em xmlns="">chaste</em> person as "refraining
        from acts or even thoughts or desires that are not virginal or not
        sanctioned by marriage vows," and defines a <em xmlns="">virgin</em> as "an
        unmarried woman devoted to religion."
      </p>
               <p>
        These various definitions suggest that people are
        <em xmlns="">restrained</em> from sexual relations with others either by physical
        or psychological damage or by devotion to certain religious tenets. The
        implication being, of course, that if it were not for these constraints,
        sexual interaction would occur. There appear to be few really
        appropriate words in the English language to describe the individual
        who, regardless of physical or emotional condition, actual sexual
        history, and marital status or ideological orientation, seems to
        <em xmlns="">prefer</em> not to engage in sexual activity. Oppressed by a
        consensus that they are nonexistent, these are the "unnoticed" who in
        this article are called "asexual"—by default.
      </p>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>FUNCTIONS AND OPPRESSION</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <p>
        The term <em xmlns="">oppression</em> often suggests an unfair and discriminatory
        distribution of rights and resources to the observable detriment of
        some. Oppressiveness can also be subtle and indirect, however, the
        result of inegalitarian principles and dynamics insidiously molding the
        attributes of societal members (Halleck, 1971: p. 22; Gil, 1973: p. 5).
        Women are acknowledged as constituting one of the most consistently
        oppressed groups in history, both directly and indirectly (Kopp, 1972:
        p. 33). According to the newly developing Function/Activity Theory of
        women's oppression, the essence of oppression lies in the assignment of
        certain functions as "natural" or "fitting" for women. "Child-bearer,"
        "child-rearer," "personal servant to the male," and "sex object" are
        cited as among the most significant of these functions (Kearon and
        Mehrof, 1971: pp. 71–72). While recognizing societal oppression of
        asexual men,<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-1" id="footnote-ref-1">
                     <sup>1</sup>
                  </a>
        the focus here is on the subtle oppression of those women who, because
        of asexual feelings, have avoided, refused or have not enjoyed the
        functions women have traditionally been obligated to perform.
      </p>
               <h3 xmlns="">THE ASEXUAL WOMAN AS ASCETIC</h3>
               <p>
        At one point in history the woman who rejected "sex-object" and
        "child-bearer" functions was lauded. A theoretical concept of sexual
        asceticism is said to have developed among Greek thinkers who seemed to
        view woman as evil and inferior and who saw salvation from the flesh for
        her through catharsis and Platonic love.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-2" id="footnote-ref-2">
                     <sup>2</sup>
                  </a>
        Some scholars believe that this Greek trend preceded and influenced the
        position eventually adopted by early Christian groups (Bullough, 1974:
        pp. 107–108). The consensus among many early spokesmen of Christianity,
        Gnosticism, Manicheanism and similar sects seemed to be that a woman,
        otherwise viewed as wicked, might become more like a man, and thereby
        gain salvation, if she elected a life of celibacy and asceticism
        (Bullough, 1974: pp. 97–120).
      </p>
               <p>
        Rather than freeing a group of women from designated female functions,
        this ideal of virginal womanhood seems to have assigned additional
        prescriptions which oppressed almost everyone. Today, many people
        continue to protest the centuries of negative impact this doctrine has
        had on vast numbers of women considered inferior for engaging in sexual
        relations with others:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          For centuries, women have (believed) that ... it is unforgivable for
          (them) to show even the slightest signs of sexual proclivity. Only in
          the last decade or two have women freed themselves of this
          irrationality. (<cite xmlns="">Glamour</cite>, March, 1974)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        The woman who may have gravitated toward this life-style because she
        really felt asexual also seems to have been oppressed. Her asexuality
        was apparently considered a religious duty. To surmount the sins of her
        gender, she was expected to live in poverty, fasting, meditating, seldom
        speaking, and in general making herself unnoticed. (Bullough, 1974: pp.
        118–119)
      </p>
               <h3 xmlns="">THE ASEXUAL WOMAN AS NEUROTIC</h3>
               <p>
        Historical changes in dominant definitions of reality seem to have
        transformed the asexual woman from a self-disciplined ascetic, to be
        awed, to a repressed neurotic, to be "cured."
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          A young virgin suffered from acute nervousness due to repressed
          desires paid a visit to a highly recommended psychiatrist. The doctor
          took one look at the voluptuous maiden and lost all his professional
          objectivity. "Take off your clothes", he ordered, scarcely able to
          disguise the lust in his voice. "Now lie down on this couch. Now close
          your eyes and very slowly spell the word <em xmlns="">bedroom</em>."
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">She began, "B—E—D—R—<em xmlns="">Oh!</em>—Ohhhhhhhhhh—Mhhhhhhhhhhh."</p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          She was cured. (<cite xmlns="">Playboy's Complete Book of Party Jokes</cite>,
          1972: p. 115)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Researchers of modern psychiatric literature have identified a trend to
        term any sexual behavior which violates traditional reproductive
        morality or which seems dysfunctional to the family as abnormal,
        disorganized or immature (Sprey, 1972: p. 88; Halleck, 1971: pp.
        104–105). Redlich and Freeman's authoritative
        <cite xmlns="">Theory and Practice of Psychiatry</cite> (1966), for example,
        labels those "patterns of sexual behavior that predominantly and
        habitually satisfy other sexual needs than those gratified by normal
        coitus" as sexual deviations or perversions (p. 384).
      </p>
               <p>
        This psychiatric consensus oppresses not only asexual women but also all
        the women who avoid, or are dissatisfied with, their "naturally
        assigned" functions. Women who engage in pre- or extra-marital sexual
        relations, prostitutes, lesbian and bisexual women could all be
        construed as violating "reproductive, family-oriented morality." Of all
        these violators, however, asexual women seem to be the most invisible.
        Rarely conceded a unique identity by therapists, professional agreement
        seems to hold that really asexual women simply do not exist.
      </p>
               <p>
        A review of the Psychological and Sociological Abstracts for the past
        ten years, for instance, uncovers almost no articles directly concerning
        women who prefer not to have sex with others. Those articles which do
        mention such women seem to explain their behavior in terms of
        "Victorianism," "premarital chastity," "religious vows" or "repressed
        homosexuality." The possibility that some women might freely prefer an
        asexual life-style is seldom explained.
      </p>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>THE AUTOEROTIC WOMAN</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <p>
        While the asexual woman, who has no sexual desires at all, is almost
        completely unrecognized, the autoerotic woman, who recognizes such
        desires but prefers to satisfy them alone, is similarly dismissed.
      </p>
               <p>
        The construction of the nonexistence of truly autoerotic women is
        illustrated by a look at some of the literature on masturbation.
        Masturbation has been defined in Hinsie and Campbells's
        <cite xmlns="">Psychiatric Dictionary</cite> as:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          ... psychologically normal during adolescence and to some event even
          in adulthood when gratification of a physical emotional relationship
          with a member of the opposite sex is impossible. (Hinsie and Campbell,
          1970: p. 453)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        This definition not only seems to imply that masturbation is
        psychologically abnormal, if an adult continues to prefer it exclusively
        when heterosexual relations are available but it also suggests the
        abnormality of homosexual people. This determination of what is abnormal
        can be interpreted as politically powerful in terms of maintenance of
        conventional mores. It seems to pressure the asexual woman to construct
        her identity <em xmlns="">out</em> of the social order and <em xmlns="">out</em> of
        reality.
      </p>
               <p>
        Therapy with the adult woman who enjoys autoerotic stimulation and
        prefers not to have sex with others therefore often includes aiding her
        to develop more mature methods of achieving satisfaction (Brooks, 1967:
        pp. 820–823; Halleck, 1971: pp. 104–105).<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-3" id="footnote-ref-3">
                     <sup>3</sup>
                  </a>
        In other words:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          Children who are told over and over again that they are liars or
          thieves become liars or thieves. People who are told over and over
          that they are crazy become crazy. If you are told over and over that
          you are a being who has profound sexual needs the odds are very good
          that you will discover that you do. Particularly when other outlets
          are forbidden or discouraged. Particularly when it is emphasized that
          those who do
          <em xmlns="">not</em> feel those needs are frigid, neurotic, sexually
          maladjusted (which for a woman means <em xmlns="">essentially</em> maladjusted)
          dried up, barren, to be pitied. (Densmore, 1971: p. 58)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Excess consensus about the sinfulness of sexual interaction has had an
        oppressive impact on the lives of generations of women. Many women who
        always stimulate themselves autoerotically or who never engage in any
        form of sexual activity may be suppressing string desires.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-4" id="footnote-ref-4">
                     <sup>4</sup>
                  </a>
        New oppression seems to lie, however, in excess psychiatric consensus
        that women who deny their "natural" female functions are just repressed
        heterosexuals in need of "a good fuck."
      </p>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>ASEXUAL AND AUTOEROTIC WOMEN</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <p>
        During the 1960's the Radical Left advocated egalitarian revolution, but
        virtually forgot to include women in their plans (Koedt, "Women and the
        Radical Movement", 1973: pp. 318–321; Willis, 1970: pp. 55–56). Asexual
        women were similarly ignored by the "sexual revolution" of that same
        decade.
      </p>
               <p>
        Fashion magazines, recognized as one barometer of stylish prescription
        in both clothing and mores, stressed the full sex lives of "liberated"
        women during this period (Tortora: 1973). By the 1970's, however, a few
        women readers were writing letters to the editors to protest:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          The tortured, belabored and endless articles on orgasm, intercourse,
          marital games, premarital sex,
          how-to-do-it-in-56-different-ways-while-playing-the-castanets and the
          evaluate-your-orgasm charts which all of you [magazines] seem
          dedicated to explore... (<cite xmlns="">Glamour</cite>, January, 1964: p. 50)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        This writer describes herself as "a devoted wife, mother of three,
        affectionate female who abhors sex." She pleaded:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          Please, would someone mention the fact that life can be beautiful,
          meaningful, rich and satisfactory with <em xmlns="">or without</em> sex? It is
          possible to adore your husband and enjoy affection while the act of
          intercourse holds anything but appeal. (Ibid.)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        While feeling that her outlook on life was "warm-blooded, knowledgeable
        and free of restraint," she seemed to believe that her existence
        dangerously contradicted accepted psychiatric tenets:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          We mustn't breathe a word of opposition, though. We must be all
          salivating at the sight of the fourposter and if not, seek therapy.
          (Ibid.)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Women sharing similar feelings wrote in support of this possibly asexual
        woman's statement:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          I wholeheartedly agree with the anonymous "Protest." (Jan.) It is
          about time that the other side of the coin was shown.
          (<cite xmlns="">Glamour</cite>, March, 1974).
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          ... I'm sure there are a lot more women in the world who feel the same
          way. I, for one, want to congratulate the woman of this article for
          speaking up for all of us who are either ashamed or afraid to do so.
          (Ibid.)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Other women also began to suggest to the magazine editors that because
        some women were being overlooked and left out of the revolution, perhaps
        the sexual liberation they publicized did not exist:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          The cataclysmic change in sexual attitudes in the latter part of the
          sixties supposedly brought relief to women, burdened for centuries by
          the hypocritical double standard. Now it seems a new rigidity is
          developing. A women is no longer free <em xmlns="">not</em> to have a sex
          life...
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          This is not a recommendation for a return to the rigid standards of
          grandma's girlhood nor a put-down of premarital sex. ... If it was
          wrong for the self-righteous of the past to condemn a woman who
          departed from society's cast-iron rule of behavior, it is also wrong
          for the disciples of today's sexual liberation to downgrade a girl who
          chooses not to participate.
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          Because a girl chooses not to have sexual relations does not make her
          a case for the analyst ... (Head, 1971: p. 76)
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          ... In many ways, sexual freedom is the philosophical toy of the
          college student. Individuals "discuss" sexual freedom all too often in
          terms that will serve only to reinforce the choice <em xmlns="">they</em> have
          made. (<cite xmlns="">Mademoiselle</cite>, Nov., 1972: p. 224)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Despite publication of these reader protests, however, fashion magazine
        editorial consensus seems to continue to popularize a
        consumption-oriented image of the sexually "liberated" woman much like
        that Una Stannard describes in her "Mask of Beauty":
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          The modern woman's liberty to expose her legs and most of her body
          does not signify women's sexual liberation, but only her obsessive
          desire to please men. Women are "free" to start wearing padded bras at
          the age of nine and to spend forty-eight million dollars annually in
          eye make-up alone. Women are free to be Playboy bunnies or to be
          topless and bottomless waitresses. Women are not free <em xmlns="">not</em> to
          be sexy. (Stannard, 1971: p. 192)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Not fitting this popular definition of "liberated," the asexual woman
        seems to only rarely receive recognition in feature articles or staff
        written columns.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-5" id="footnote-ref-5">
                     <sup>5</sup>
                  </a>
        When one recent column did mention "celibate" women, its author's
        partial motive seemed to be nullification of their
        "news-worthiness"—their public existence:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          One of the women at the speakout described <em xmlns="">her</em> sexual style
          as celibacy. And recently I read a newspaper article by a woman who
          said she and her friends believed that celibacy was a "valid sexual
          alternative." Could this be a trend? If so, what could the media
          possibly make of this most non-of-non-events? With any luck, not a
          thing. (Durbin, 1975: p. 24)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <h3 xmlns="">THE ASEXUAL AND AUTOEROTIC WOMAN AS POLITICALLY CONSCIOUS</h3>
               <p>
        One of the women referred to by the <cite xmlns="">Mademoiselle</cite> columnist
        was addressing the Second Annual Conference on Sexuality sponsored by
        the New York chapter of the National Organization of Women (NOW).
        Although the columnist's remarks suggest a personal contempt for
        "celibate" women, the theme of her article revolves around the
        manufacture of sexual fashion, which she feels was reflected at the
        conference. Autoeroticism and asexuality, once recommended as a
        demonstration of religious consciousness, are beginning, in some sectors
        of the feminist movement, to be recommended as one demonstration of
        political consciousness.
      </p>
               <p>
        The origin of this newly developing imperative may partially lie in
        feminist analysis of a growing body of research about vaginal orgasms.
        The scientific investigations of Kinsey and also Masters and Johnson
        exposed the vaginal orgasm as a hoax by indicating that the clitoris,
        rather than the vagina, functions in producing orgasm. (Koedt, 1973a:
        201–203)
      </p>
               <p>
        On the basis of this evidence, many feminists have evaluated the theory
        of the "vaginal orgasm" as exploitative in its assumption that only the
        mature, submissive woman, who accepted her "natural" functions, could
        enjoy it (Atkinson, 1970: p.42; Koedt, 1973a: pp. 199–200)
      </p>
               <p>
        Rejecting the vaginal orgasm as a myth created to ensure female sexual
        dependence on the male, some feminists recognized clitoral orgasm as
        opening up sexual options for women (Koedt, 1973a: pp. 204–206;
        Atkinson, 1970: p. 42; <cite xmlns="">The Feminists</cite> ..., 1970: pp.
        117–118).
      </p>
               <p>
        Backed scientifically by new evidence that sex may be an "acquired
        habit, appetite or even addiction" rather than a "biological force"
        (Wright, 1972: p. 119), the idea of options may have encouraged some
        women in the Liberation Movement who feel asexual or autoerotic to talk
        about their lives. (Densmore, 1971: p. 59)
      </p>
               <p>
        Other feminists, repulsed by the idea of sexual involvement with men
        who, they feel, oppress and even despise them, have begun to equate
        sexual options with political strategy (Bernard, 1972: p. 373):
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          The moving nucleus of feminism is a gradual accretion of women
          defining themselves irrevocably as political lesbians, women sexually
          celibate or asexual or lesbian in the traditional sense of the word,
          who perceive the bonding of women in every phase of existence as the
          sine qua non of feminist revolution. (Johnston, 1973)
        </p>
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          We must destroy the institution of heterosexual sex which is a
          manifestation of the male-female role. Since physical pleasure can be
          achieved in both sexes by autoerotic acts, sex as a social act is
          psychologically in nature; at present its psychology is
          dominance-passivity. (<cite xmlns="">The Feminists</cite> ..., 1970: pp.
          117–118)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        In seeking to liberate women, the advocates of these strategies may be
        inviting yet another tyranny. A consensus which praises women who do not
        have sex with men as politically conscious might alleviate the
        oppression of traditionally assigned female functions, but would
        probably create new oppressive functions. The woman who still wants to
        have sex with men might function as "scapegoat" and the woman who feels
        asexual or autosexual might function as a political symbol—her identity
        still lost in the slogans, and her reality going unnoticed.
      </p>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>CONCLUSION</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <p>
        Asexual and autoerotic women seem seldom to have been accorded the equal
        right to be different, the equal right to celebrate their unique
        experiences in the world. For their violation of established female
        function, they have been oppressed by a societal consensus that they, as
        free and unique individuals, do not exist. Again and again, their
        personal experiences have been redefined for them in terms of socially
        constructed meanings: they are "ascetic," "neurotic," "unliberated," or
        "politically conscious." Their sexual preferences are explained away in
        the rhetoric of whatever sexual ideology seems currently to be in vogue.
      </p>
               <p>
        The assumption that members of certain groups, as a function of their
        being so identified, need help may be one force in the perpetuation of
        this kind of consensual redefinition of experience. When women as a
        group were considered sexually sinful, those women who preferred not to
        have sexual relations with others were often "helped" in their struggle
        with evil through religious asceticism. When women as a group came to be
        viewed as performing important sexual and reproductive functions for
        men, those women who preferred not to have sexual relations with others
        were frequently "helped" by therapy in working through their
        neuroticism. Now that women as a group are beginning to be redefined as
        "oppressed" in their relationships with men, those women who prefer not
        to have sexual relations with others are sometimes "helped" in their
        struggle for "consciousness" through political support.
      </p>
               <p>
        One possible explanation for this "helping" system might be that because
        these asexual and autoerotic women are different they must be
        "consensually redefined," "fitted into" and "understood" in the gestalt
        of the dominant, or alternative, society in question in order to avoid
        social upheaval. In this context, religion, therapy and politics might
        all be viewed as mechanisms of social control useful in maintaining the
        reality of established ideas against serious challenge.
      </p>
               <h3 xmlns="">HELPING ASEXUAL AND AUTOEROTIC WOMEN TO BE THEMSELVES</h3>
               <p>
        In the framework of this broad kind of social policy perspective, women
        who, for a portion or all of their lives, feel asexual or autoerotic may
        cease to be victims only when people no longer feel a need to
        conceptualize each other in terms of the "functions" they can
        perform—when the "sexual is dissolved into the fully personal ... and
        ... sexual ideologies are discarded." (Wright, 1972: p. 121)
      </p>
               <p>
        Pat allusions to sweeping changes in social structure, however, can
        sometimes oversimplify the complexity of life. These generalizations can
        easily become just another way of ignoring the individual uniqueness of
        human beings; an excuse for not attempting to provide relief for those
        people now in psychic pain.Black psychiatrists, for example, have
        angrily cried "racism" against the contentions of some of their
        colleagues that they cannot effectively treat black patients until the
        prejudiced attitudes of the society which oppresses them have been
        altered (Thomas and Sillen, 1972: p. 139). A similar analogy could be
        made regarding asexual and autoerotic women.
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          If you have an alive body, no one can tell you how to experience the
          world. And no one can tell you what truth is, because you experience
          it. The body does not lie. (Keleman in Braun, 1975: p. 9)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Some of the newest therapies do propose, at least on paper, that the aim
        of therapy should be to furnish support and insight for the individual's
        life-style, with acceptance and respect for his or her individuality
        (Vocations for Social Change, 1975: p. 106; Grimstead and Rennie, 1975:
        p. 60).
      </p>
               <p>
        While the power of politics to group and redefine the life experiences
        of asexual and autoerotic women can be illustrated by a look at some
        camps of the feminist movement, other feminists interpret feminism as
        freeing all women to express their sexual uniqueness in an atmosphere of
        acceptance:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          Sex can be expressed with a woman, with a man, with a group of people,
          alone or not practiced at all. (Mander and Rush, 1974: p. 24)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        Going unnoticed in society, being told that one doesn't feel what one
        feels but that, indeed, one feels something else can be a very painful
        and even debilitating experience for some women. Feminist
        consciousness-raising sessions and group therapies are beginning,
        hopefully, to work like this in exploring such problems:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          If a woman continually blames herself for her inadequacies ... the
          group works with her to explore what part is her responsibility and
          what part is imposed on her by society. Thus she is at the same time
          encouraged to assume responsibility and to relinquish responsibility
          for the part that is not hers so that she can be freed of that burden
          and grow. (Mander and Rush, 1974: p. 17)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        This can often increase the awareness "that there is in fact nothing
        wrong with the tormented individual, but a great deal wrong with the
        social circumstances which limit her life choices" (Grimstad and Rennie,
        1975: p. 66).
      </p>
               <p>
        Some women coming to grips with their longtime feelings that they prefer
        not to have sex with others—and others who are initially recognizing
        these feelings after perhaps years of involvement in lesbian or
        heterosexual activities—may want support in making their transition.
      </p>
               <p>
        Even autoerotic women may have orgasmic difficulties. In fact, one
        serious drawback of the Masters and Johnson type of sex therapy for
        these women is its emphasis on working with couples, thus excluding
        women who are single, temporarily between sex partners, or autoerotic in
        orientation (Grimstad and Rennie, 1975: pp. 54–55).
      </p>
               <p>
        Alfred Kinsey (1953) demonstrated that not everyone has or maintains one
        exclusive sexual preference throughout an entire lifetime. The woman who
        has felt asexual or autoerotic and is beginning to feel differently may
        want support in the transition to another point on the sexual continuum:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          When celibacy no longer feels good we should get out of it—but that's
          easier said than done. And it feels harder the longer we have been
          celibate. Coming out of celibacy, we may feel embarrassed by needs
          that seem insatiable. (Boston Women's Health Book Collective, 1973: p.
          44)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <p>
        It is recognized, of course, that a few women may have very deep and
        complex difficulties which cannot simply be attributed to society. They
        may exhibit asexual or autoerotic behavior while really wanting
        something entirely different or even because of fear of any kind of
        physical intimacy.
      </p>
               <p>
        "Helping," therefore, takes on the discriminatory tone that robs women
        of the truth of individual experiences when it makes them victims of
        excess consensus, with the underlying assumption being that
        <em xmlns="">all</em> or <em xmlns="">most</em> asexual or autoerotic women, because of
        their orientations, <em xmlns="">need</em> help.
      </p>
               <p>
        If a woman feels that she does want help in any of these areas she
        should realize that the political biases of therapists, whether
        conscious or unconscious, frequently influence their work (Halleck,
        1971). Thus, she might want to interview prospective therapists to see
        if she will be able to work with them without having the truth of her
        life altered to fit another truth.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-6" id="footnote-ref-6">
                     <sup>6</sup>
                  </a>
               </p>
               <p>
        Before an asexual or autoerotic woman decides on sometimes expensive
        professional guidance, however, she might first try tapping the
        strengths within herself. The following is a description of a woman
        learning to love the appearance of her physical body, but the concept
        involved could as easily be applied to an asexual or autoerotic woman
        accepting the uniqueness of her life:
      </p>
               <blockquote xmlns="">
                  <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
          I stood as through I were proud before I was proud, and then I became
          proud. (Braun, 1975: p. 16)
        </p>
               </blockquote>
               <docTitle>
                  <titlePart>REFERENCES AND RECOMMENDED READINGS</titlePart>
               </docTitle>
               <ul xmlns="">
                  <li>
          ATKINSON, TI-GRACE. "The Institution of Sexual Intercourse." In
          <cite>Notes from the Second Year: Women's Liberation</cite>, edited by
          Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt. New York: Radical Feminism, 1970.
        </li>
                  <li>
          BARNARD, JESSIE. "Women, Marriage and the Future." In
          <cite>Intimate Life Styles: Marriage and Its Alternatives</cite>,
          edited by Joann S. DeLora and Jack R. DeLora. Pacific Palisades,
          Calif.: Goodyear Publishing Co., Inc., 1972.
        </li>
                  <li>
                     <cite>Boston After Dark</cite>, February 25, 1975. p. 6.</li>
                  <li>
          Boston Women's Health Book Collective.
          <cite>Our Bodies, Our Selves</cite>. New York: Simon and Schuster,
          1973.
        </li>
                  <li>
          BRAUN, SAUL, ed. <cite>Catalog of Sexual Consciousness</cite>. New
          York: Grove Press, Inc., 1975.
        </li>
                  <li>
          BROOKS, PATRICIA A. "Masturbation,"
          <cite>American Journal of Nursing</cite> (1967), pp. 820–823.
        </li>
                  <li>
          BULLOUGH, VERN L.
          <cite>The Subordinate Sex: A History of Attitudes Toward Women</cite>.
          Baltimore: Penguin Books, Inc., 1974.
        </li>
                  <li>
                     <cite>Cosmopolitan's Love Guide</cite>. New York: Cosmopolitan
          Magazine, 1972.
        </li>
                  <li>
          DENSMORE, DANA. "Independence from the Sexual Revolution." In
          <cite>Notes from the Third Year: Women's Liberation</cite>, edited by
          Shulamith Firestone and Anne Koedt. New York: Notes from the Second
          Year, Inc., 1971.
        </li>
               </ul>
               <hr xmlns=""/>
               <footer xmlns="">
                  <ol>
                     <li id="footnote-1">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
              The oppression of asexual men in contemporary American society is
              illustrated by Perry Deane Young's remark in
              <cite xmlns="">Ms Magazine</cite> (March, 1975) that Vietnam served as an
              escape hatch for some men from "Back home ... where men and women
              were expected to move in couples." "Any sort of eccentricity (in
              sexual or other behavior) was tolerated in Vietnam so long as one
              behaved properly in combat. This allowed for those loners who
              wanted nothing to do with any kind of sex involving another
              person" (p.116). The same sort of oppression applies to women, but
              combat is not usually available as a solution for them.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-1">↩︎</a>
                        </p>
                     </li>
                     <li id="footnote-2">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
              Pythagoras is reported to have identified women with the
              "unlimited principle" of "badness" and "darkness." He seemed to
              believe that the soul could be saved only through catharsis, which
              was achieved, in part, by avoiding sexual consummation. While
              Plato is said to have indicated in his <cite xmlns="">Timaeus</cite> that
              women needed men sexually, (Bullough, 1974: pp. 60–61) he later
              developed the concept of Platonic love. According to this idea,
              happiness apparently could only be gained through "sacred," or
              non-physical love (Bullough, 1974: pp.107–108).<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-2">↩︎</a>
                        </p>
                     </li>
                     <li id="footnote-3">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
              The fantasies which often accompany masturbation have sometimes
              been used as evidence that those whose total sexual outlet
              consists of autostimulation are repressed. Masturbation is seen as
              having an "interpersonal quality ... in which ... wishes regarding
              relationships with another can be fulfilled" (Koff, 1972: p. 55).
              While this is undoubtedly true for many people, it is popularly
              acknowledged that many others entertain fantasies involving exotic
              settings and unusual circumstances which they never intend to
              actually act out:
            </p>
                        <blockquote>
                           <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                "Anything goes in fantasy. It's a healthy out for desires you'd
                <em xmlns="">never</em> act on. So feel free! Fantasize whatever pleases
                you (lesbianism, group sex, fetishism, voyeurism,
                exhibitionism)—you'll soon be floating into another hazy realm."
                (<cite xmlns="">Cosmopolitan Love Guide</cite>, 1972: pp. 54–55)<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-3">↩︎</a>
                           </p>
                        </blockquote>
                     </li>
                     <li id="footnote-4">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
              Kinsey's research indicated that while masturbation was the most
              important sexual outlet for the unmarried females in his sample,
              about 2 per cent of the women studied said they had never
              recognized sexual arousal under any conditions. (Kinsey, 1953: pp.
              512–525)<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-4">↩︎</a>
                        </p>
                     </li>
                     <li id="footnote-5">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
              This statement is based on the author's review of three
              wide-circulation magazines (<cite xmlns="">Glamour</cite>,
              <cite xmlns="">Mademoiselle</cite>, and <cite xmlns="">Seventeen</cite>) from
              January 1970 through January 1975.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-5">↩︎</a>
                        </p>
                     </li>
                     <li id="footnote-6">
                        <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                           <cite xmlns="">Guidelines for Women Seeking Psychotherapy</cite> provides
              detailed advice on how to select a therapist. It is available from
              Cleveland Women's Counseling, P.O. Box 18472, Cleveland, Ohio
              44118 for 50¢ per copy.<a xmlns="" href="#footnote-ref-6">↩︎</a>
                        </p>
                     </li>
                  </ol>
               </footer>
            </div>
         </body>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
